All right, folks. Let's wait a couple
more seconds and let it begin.
All
right.
So, let's begin.
We're going to continue our series on
training neural networks. Specifically,
we're going to talk about using gradient
descent to train networks. Now, in the
last class, we saw how to set up the
problem of training a network to model a
function. We're given uh training input
output pairs from our target function.
We com now for any one of these inputs
the network computes an actual output.
So we compute the average d we define a
divergence between the output of the
network and the desired output. We
compute the average divergence over the
entire training set. This is our
empirical risk which we call our loss.
This loss is a function only of the
network parameters and we estimate our
network parameters to minimize this
loss. So this is actually an instance of
function minimization. Our loss is a
function of the network parameters and
we are finding the parameters that
minimize this loss. Now so before we
proceed, we'll just quickly go over the
basics of function optimization with an
initial discussion on derivatives.
So I'm just throwing this back out to
you.
What do you understand by the term
derivative?
Can anybody tell me what you understand
by the term derivative?
What is a derivative?
If I have a function f ofx, instant rate
of change. Okay. Variation.
Variation. Slope of change. Slope of
change. Everything else. Rate of change
of a variable with respect to the other.
Rate of change. slow how one thing
changes. So these are all kind of
correct but not complete for reasons
that I will talk mention briefly. The
derivative of a function at any point
tells us tells us how much a minute
increment to the argument of the
function will increase the value of the
function. So for any function y = f ofx
this derivative is expressed in as a
multiplier alpha which multiplies the
increment delta x to give you the
corresponding increment delta y.
So uh this relationship is based on the
fact that at a fine enough resolution
any smooth continuous function is
locally linear at any point. It's
important to note something here. This
is the only correct way to define a
derivative. Now, in school, you might
have used the notation dy over dx.
This works sometimes, but doesn't always
work. Can anybody tell me why this is
not a good universal notation for
derivatives?
Anyone? Why is dy over dx not a good
universal notation for derivatives?
Anybody?
undefined.
It's could be defined, right? Partial
dependency. If dx is zero, it's cause
problems. Doesn't include multiple
variables. Here's the thing. This only
works when x is a scalar. If x is a
vector, can I write 1 / dx? When dx is a
vector, this is not an this is not a
proper notation. So uh uh this the the
only correct way to think about
derivatives is as the multiplier that
multiplies an increment in x to give you
the corresponding increment in y.
And so uh that's what we we are going to
use now for scalar functions of scalar
variables y and x are scalar. Then the
derivative alpha over here is the scalar
value by which you multiply delta x the
increment in x delta x to get the
corresponding increment in y delta y.
And because both y and x are scalers,
delta y and delta x are also scalers.
And so here it's okay to represent the
derivative as dy / dx. Although the
notation frime of x is more appropriate.
Why would I say that this is more
appropriate?
Anybody? Why is this more appropriate
as a notation? Anyone?
So,
take a guess. Better for talking about
function optimization. Any other
guesses?
Because it looks simple. No, the reason
is it's making it explicit that it
depends on X. The derivative depends on
the location. Here the derivative,
you know, incrementing X increments Y.
Here incrementing X will decrement Y. In
some locations, an increment of X will
result in a very small increment of Y.
In other other locations, a small
increment of X will increase result in a
large increment of Y. So the actual
derivative is dependent on the
value x the value of x at which you're
computing it. So frimex of x is a better
notation even though dy / dx is just
fine for scalar variables. Now when you
go to multivate now the derivative of a
function at any point is actually the
rate of change of the function at the
point the slope of the function. If
increasing x increases f ofx then the
derivative will be positive. So in all
of these regions where increasing as you
go right the function increases those
will have positive derivative. If
increasing x decreases the function
value then you're going to have for
positive delta x delta y will be
negative and so your derivatives are
going to be negative. In both cases if
the function is steep the derivative
will be large in magnitude. If the
function is shallow, it will be small in
magnitude. And if the function is
locally flat like in these regions, then
where it's just not increasing or
decreasing, then at these locations
shown by these red lines, the derivative
will be zero. So all of this you guys
are familiar with.
Now
when you get to multivariate functions,
things get a little more complicated. If
you have a scalar function, y is a
scalar of a vector input. X is X is a
vector, then X can be thought of as this
vector term with many components X1
through XD. So any increment in X delta
X will also be a vector with the same
number of components delta you know
delta X1 through delta XD.
So
clearly I cannot write d / dx because
you cannot divide by a vector. You can
see clearly that
this notation is will still work. So the
increment delta y if if I take a a step
delta x from any x this results in a
change delta y and the increment delta y
is related to delta x through a
multiplier alpha. and alpha is the
derivative. Now if delta x is a column
vector, what can you tell me about the
row vector
about about alpha? I just gave away the
answer. If delta x is a column vector,
delta y is a scalar. What is alpha?
Anybody?
What kind of vector is alpha?
It's got to be a row vector, right? We
can only multiply a column vector by a
row vector. And so the derivative of a
scalar function with respect to a column
vector argument is going to be a row
vector. And the relationship between the
uh the increment in the output and the
increment in the input is assumed to be
linear. And the multiplier that gives
you delta y
from delta x is the derivative. And this
is going to be a row vector. So alpha is
going to have this form over here.
Now
uh
I can do something else. Alpha has many
components, right? And each alpha I
corresponds to one of the components of
delta of of delta x. So alpha 1
multiplies delta x1, alpha 2 multiplies
delta x2 and so on. What is alpha r? Now
in the multivaried case delta x can be
anything. So I can choose an increment
delta x where where only the first
component is incremented and the others
are not incremented. This is a valid
delta x. And when this happens the
multiplier that multiplies this guy to
give you delta y that only gives you the
contribution of x1. So that is what is
called a partial derivative of y with
respect to x1. It is the increment in y
when only x1 is incremented and the rest
are not. So each of these alpha i is
going to be a partial derivative with
respect to one of the arguments and
alpha itself is going to be a row vector
consisting of all of these partial
derivatives.
So I'm going to be uh using this ter
this this uh notation
this inverted triangle y of x to
represent derivatives. Once again this
is just the alpha that I gave you
earlier. But I'm using this notation
this inverted triangle is called naba
naba y of x which means that this is the
output of the function. This is the
argument of the function and this is
telling you how y responds to increments
in x and once again the relationship is
delta y is the derivative times delta x
and this derivative is in fact a row
vector consisting of the partial
derivatives of y with respect to the
individual axis. Now those of you who
have any any familiarity with the
subject might have heard the term
gradient. The gradient is in fact
defined as the transpose of the
derivative.
So any questions so far? Is that clear
to everybody what we discussed?
Is this clear to everybody so far? Give
me thumbs ups. I'm looking at the thumbs
up. Yes. Okay.
All right. So let me continue
now.
The derivative of a scalar function f
ofx with respect to a multivariate input
is therefore a multiplicative factor
that gives us the change in f ofx for
tiny variations in x. It's a row vector
consisting of the partial derivatives of
the function with respect to the
individual components of x. The gradient
is defined as the transpose of this
derivative. But then what does this
derivative actually mean? What is this
guy? What does it signify? Does anybody
have an idea? What does this derivative
really mean? Anybody have an idea?
I'll wait a few seconds then I'll move
on. Right. Anyway,
direction of steepest ascent. Right. And
we'll see how
this guy over here as you can see it's a
vector inner product. It's an inner
product between this vector and this
vector. This is basically just the
transpose of the gradient, right? So
let's consider the behavior of inner
products themselves.
when I compute the inner product of two
vectors
uh the uh if you have any two vectors u
and v the inner product of the two
vectors you're all familiar is simply
given by the magnitude of u * the
magnitude of v * cos theta where theta
is the angle between the two. So as the
angle between the two vectors changes,
you can see how the inner product
changes. When the two vectors are
aligned, the inner product is maximum.
As one vector goes away from the other,
it begins falling. And when the two are
exactly opposite, the inner product is
minimum. And then as it comes back and
becomes gets aligned, it goes back to
the maximum. So the angle between the
the inner product is maximum when the
angle between the two is 0°. As you can
see from this uh from this little
animation. Now if I consider the uh
gradient again
the increment in y is the inner product
between the derivative and dx. Now this
derivative is a property of the
function. It's not something that you
can change. So at any point x the
derivative has some direction and this
is fixed. What you can change is dx. So
if you're at some x you can step it you
can take a step dx in many different
directions and say the derivative is out
here. If you keep this step size fixed
and you keep changing the direction of
dx itself
when will this inner product be maximum?
Anybody? When is this inner product
going to be maximum?
Somebody answer me.
When the angle is zero. Right? So in
other words, the increment DF is going
to be maximum when the when the
increment the incre the increment in the
value of the function is going to be
maximum when the step you take is in the
same direction as the gradient. And so
the gradient is the uh direction in
which you take a step to to it's it's
the direction of steepest asset. So from
this location you can take a you can
take steps in many different directions
but if you walk in the direction of the
gradient that's when the function is
going to increase fastest.
And conversely, if you uh walk opposite
the gradient in the opposite direction.
So if you walk in this direction, the
function increases fastest. If you walk
exactly opposite it, that's when the
function decreases fastest. This is the
direction of steepest descent. And when
the function is at a minimum
then where the function is flat right
there if you take a small step a tiny
step in any direction the function
doesn't really change and so here the
gradient is going to be zero that make
sense to everybody
that the gradient is the direction of
the steepest ascent
that you have to walk exactly opposite
the gradient if you want to decrease the
function fastest and at minima the
gradient is going to be zero.
So uh there's another property of
gradients which is that uh if you slice
the function at any height then the edge
that you get say this one that is what
is called a level set. This is the set
of all axis where the value of the
function is constant and it can be
proved that the gradient is always at
90° to the level set. So this is this is
a property we use sometimes. We can also
there's another derivative that you can
also compute which is uh uh the so which
is the second derivative of a fun of the
function with respect to the input
vector the argument and this is called
the hessen. This will be a matrix where
the igth component of the matrix is the
partial derivative of the function with
respect to the iat and the j components
of the input. This matrix the hessen
will be positive definite at minima. And
if you don't know what a positive
definite means or what or the general
notion of what I just mentioned uh just
take into consideration that this matrix
is going to have all positive values at
minima and at other other locations the
igen values can be positive or negative.
Now exactly how that happens is
something I'll explain in a later class.
So that leads us to our first poll.
Let me release my password.
Five seconds, guys.
I'll stop this very shortly because
we run out of time. All right.
Okay. Let me end it. One minute.
So
anybody want to answer the first
question?
Select all that are true about the
derivatives of the scale scalar function
f ofx at any location x. There may be
many directions in which we can step
such that f ofx increases. True or
false?
True. Okay. The direction of the
gradient is the direction in which the
function increases fastest. True or
false? True. The gradient is the
derivative of f ofx with respect to x.
True or false?
It's false. Why is it false?
Why is it false?
The gradient is the transpose of the
derivative. Right? If f of x is a scalar
function of an n cross one column
vector, what is the shape of the
derivative of y with respect to x?
What's the shape of the derivative over
here? It's 1 + n. Lovely. You guys got
it all right? So, we're good. Let's
continue.
So, let's return to our problem. And
this is the problem of uh function
optimization. You're given a function.
I'm just going to speak in generic
terms. You're given a function f ofx of
a variable x. x could be scalar like in
the top left example or it could be a
vector. And like here.
So let's have a quiz first to ex uh to
help you recall how we did this in
school. For functions of a scalar, the
location of the minimum is generally
where the derivative is zero. being a
minimum means that the function value is
higher all around it. So it doesn't
matter which direction you approach the
function from whether whether it's from
the right or for the left from the left
the function will keep decreasing till
it gets to the minimum and then it keeps
increasing. So right here the derivative
is going to be zero. So to identify the
minimum you just you only need to find
or you you need to find where the
derivative of the function is zero. I
assume you you guys all remember this
from school. Do you remember this from
school
over here? Okay. But is this a
sufficient condition for this to be a
minimum?
Is this a sufficient condition for this
to be no? Okay. And so let's go to our
second poll.
I'm going to give you only 40 seconds
for this one, guys.
So 20 seconds to go.
Okay,
let me end this.
All right.
Uh,
so
someone want to answer this question.
Number three is correct, right? You want
the derivative to be zero, but the
second derivative must be positive. Why
so? Because both maxima and minima are
turning points. In the case of maxima,
as you approach it from any direction,
the function initially increases till
you hit the maximum, then it begins
decreasing. For the minima, as you
approach it from any direction, the
function initially decreases and then it
begins increasing. So if you consider
the derivative at the maximum
to the left of the maximum the function
is increasing. So over here the
derivative is going to be positive. To
the right of the maximum the function is
decreasing. So over here the derivative
is going to be negative. In the case of
the minimum to the left of the minimum
the function is decreasing. So the
derivative is going to be negative. But
then to the right of the function the
function is increasing. So the
derivative is going to be positive. So
if I plot the derivative, here is what
you will get.
At the maximum, the derivative is
positive. Although it's decreasingly
positive, it becomes zero exactly at the
maximum and then it becomes negative and
begins and becomes increasingly
negative. At the minimum, the derivative
is minimum although is negative although
it's decreasingly negative. And right at
the minimum, it becomes zero. And then
after the minimum the derivative becomes
positive because the function begins to
increase. So this red curve shows you
what the derivative looks like. Now what
is the derivative of the red curve at
the maximum?
Is it going to be positive or negative
out here?
What is it going to be here? Is the
derivative going to be positive or
negative? It's going to be negative
because increasing x decreases this
value. At the minimum, the derivative is
going to be positive. Increasing x
increases this value. And so that's why
you check the second derivative. The
second derivative is negative at maximum
and positive at minimum. And so we have
this check, right? You're going to first
find a uh location where the derivative
is zero. then you double check you check
the double derivative at that solution
and if it's positive then it's a minimum
if it's negative it's a maximum this is
what you learned in school
now uh not all locations where the
derivative is zero are turning points
though here at a maximum the derivative
is zero it is a turning point at a
minimum the derivative is zero it's a
turning point but you also have these
things like inflection points now at the
inlection ction point here is a place
where the function was decreasing
and then slowed down and then continued
to decrease. So right here the
derivative is going to be zero but to
the left of it the derivative is
negative because the function is
decreasing. To the right of it also the
derivative is negative because the
function is decreasing. So the shape of
the derivative is going to be the
derivative curve is going to look
something like this. Now if you had a
function which was say like this guy,
what would the derivative curve look
like for this one? Anybody?
If you had a function like this one,
what would the derivative curve look
like?
Someone want to take want to guess? It's
going to be zero out here, but to the
left it's positive and to the right it's
positive. So it's going to be something
like this, right? And so at these
inflection points, the derivative
doesn't go from being positive to
negative or from being negative to
positive. It basically stays on the same
side of the of zero. So the second
derivative ends up also being zero at
these guys more often than not. And so
you need additional tests.
And when it gets to multiple variables,
it gets to be a little more complex.
At inflection points, the derivative
itself becomes flat as you can see. And
so the second derivative also tends to
be zero. Uh even for functions of scalar
variables, multivaried functions, we'll
see more about this in coming classes,
but it gets to be pretty challenging.
So nonetheless for functions of multiple
multi multiple variables minima are
still turning points meaning it doesn't
matter which direction you are you you
approach it from uh regardless of
whether you approach it from here. So if
you're approaching it from here and walk
this way the function will decrease and
then begin increasing after the minimum.
If you approach it in this direction
then to the function will decrease and
then begin increasing after after you
cross the minimum. So the minima are
always turning points even in uh fun
functions of multiple variables. So to
find a minimum or any turning point we
must find a point where shifting in any
direction by a microscopic amount will
not change the value of the function.
basically places where the derivative is
zero and so the minimum of a function
will be a turning point where the
gradient is zero. We must find this
location
and to find the minimum therefore we're
going to solve for solve this equation.
We will compute the derivative of the
function which is a vector as we saw and
equate it to zero and find the value x
at which the function is zero. Then you
would compute the hessen at this
candidate solution to verify that the
hessen is positive definite to identify
local minimum. If it's negative
definite, it will be local maximum. So I
promised you that I to give you some
more information about the hessen. What
is this hessen? Now this has to do with
the fact that in multiple uh variables
you can actually approach
a point from multiple directions. For
example, you could walk like this and go
past this point or you can walk like
this and still go past this point or you
could walk like this and still go past
this point. There are many ways of
approaching this point. So consider a
function like this over here. If you
walked in this direction,
this is a minimum. If you walked in this
direction, this is still a minimum. So
there are two orthogonal directions and
in each direction, this remains a
minimum.
So if you took the equation of the curve
as you walked along this direction and
you took the second derivative, it's
going to be positive here. If you took
the equation of the curve as you walked
along this direction and took the second
derivative over here, it's still going
to be positive. So this is an overall
minimum. Now consider this guy here. If
you walk in this direction
right here, this guy is going to be a
minimum. If you walk in this direction,
this guy is going to be a maximum. So
this direction, in this direction, the
second derivative is going to be
positive. In this direction the second
derivative is going to be negative. Now
the when you I perform decomposition of
the of the Hessen matrix the Hessen
matrix is going to give you the two
principal directions of maximum
variation. And
if the derivatives are positive in all
these directions it's going to be a
minimum if the second derivatives are
positive. And if the second derivatives
are you know have varied signs then in
for some it's a minimum and for some
it's a maximum and the second derivative
just happens to be the igon values of
this hessen matrix and these principal
directions happen to be the igon vectors
of the hessen matrix. So if you want to
find out if something is a minimum or
not, you'd have to perform an iggon
decomposition of the hessen. It's going
to give you the principal directions of
variation. And then you check the igen
vectors in both direction in all the
directions. If all of them are positive,
it's a minimum. If some of them are
positive and some of them are negative,
then it's a it's what is called a saddle
point where it's a minimum in some
directions and maximum in other
directions.
directions. Did that make sense to
everybody?
This little description of Hessen, did
that make sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Right. So good.
And so that's why you check the Hessen
to determine the vectors of the values
of the Hessen to decide if it's a
positive if it's a if it's a minimum or
a maximum. If the Hessen is positive
definite, all values are positive, it's
a minimum. If all all values are
negative, it's a maximum. Otherwise, it
can be anything.
So far so good. Now solving things in
this manner is fine. But often it is
simply not possible to solve this
equation. Just equate the derivative of
the function to zero because the
equation may not even have a nice closed
form that you can equate to zero and
solve. In these situations, we're going
to need an iterative solution where we
begin with a guess for the optimal x and
then uh iteratively refine it till the
correct value is obtained. So in the
iterative procedure, if you have a
function of this kind or this kind, you
start off with an initial guess. You say
I think the minimum is here. Then you
check you find that it's not the
minimum. So then you step away from it.
And you want to step in a promising
direction where you're likely to find
the minimum. And then you take a step.
You arrive at a new point. Then you
check again. Am I at a minimum? And if
it's not, then you take another step.
And you keep doing this until it feels
as if you've arrived at the minimum. It
doesn't matter whether whether it's a
function of one variable or multiple
variables. This is the basic principle
that we're going to use. So did this
make sense to all of you guys? this
iterative uh estimation of the minimum.
Did this make sense?
Right. Okay.
So, which direction will we step in?
What is this promising direction?
Every time you take a step, you want to
decrease the function. So, you're going
to start off with an initial estimate
and then you want to find a direction in
which moving in that direction decreases
the function. Now consider this. If the
function is decreasing,
what will the derivative of the function
be? Will it be positive or negative? If
the function is decreasing, will it be
positive or negative?
Negative. Right? If the function is
increasing, will the derivative be
positive or negative?
It's going to be positive. So let's say
I'm at this location
and I check the derivative.
I find the derivative to be negative.
So will going forward decrease the
function or increase it?
What will happen? It will decrease it.
Right? Whereas if at another location I
find the derivative to be positive will
going forward decrease the function or
increase it?
it's going to increase it. This is the
basic principle that we're going to use.
What we will do is we're going to start
off uh at some initial location.
Then you're going to check the
derivative of the function over there.
If the derivative is zero, then you're
at a turning point or an inflection. But
if the derivative is not zero, if the
derivative is positive
then if the derivative like over here
the derivative is positive then you know
that go going forward will increase the
function. So if the derivative is
positive should you be taking a step
forward or should you be taking a step
backward to decrease the function? What
would it be backwards? Right? If the
derivative is negative,
should you be taking a step forward or
backward?
Forward. Right? So that's the simple
test. You're going to check the sign of
the derivative. If the derivative is
positive, you take a step backwards.
Like here, if the derivative is
negative, you take a step forward. This
is the very simple iterative solution
that we're going to use to find the
minimum. You start off with an initial
guess. At each point, you're going to
check the sign of the derivative. If the
derivative is positive, you know, if
it's zero, you may be at a minimum.
Otherwise, if the derivative is
positive, you take a step back. If the
derivative is negative, you take a step
forward. And you keep doing this till
you arrive at a at a minimum. Now, I can
write these two steps in a single
equation like so. How? I can say I'm
going to take a step that is equals the
sign of the derivative times some step.
Observe that if the derivative is
positive, this sign is going to be plus,
which means that I'm taking a step
backwards. If the derivative is
negative, this sign is going to be
minus. Minus and minus will become plus.
And so I'm going to be taking a step
forward. So this single equation
encapsulates both both conditions in a
single you know in a single formula.
This making sense to all of you guys
right.
So Bruno what was the question here?
What was the d
um I cannot pinpoint where we mix the
equation together. I just understand
when they are separated.
>> I couldn't hear you clearly but again
you agreed that if the derivative is
positive you want to go back right? If
the derivative is negative you want to
go forward. So what I can do is take a
step size and then I can check I can say
minus the sign of the derivative. So if
the derivative is positive it means
because this is positive this is
positive I'm going backwards right and
whereas here if the derivative is
negative this is negative this is
negative both will combine to become a
plus and so I'll end up taking a step
forward so this is an iterative solution
at each point x k is the k step and then
the k + one iteration follows this
formula I'm going to assume that this
made sense to everybody if it didn't
please you pick it up on PL and answer.
Okay, so let's continue. I'm going to
collapse this to one more thing. Instead
of just using the sign of the
derivative, I'm going to use the entire
derivative itself.
So this is not substantially different
from this one. I'm still using the sign
of the derivative, but I'm also using
the magnitude of the derivative. And
this is going to be my update rule. Now,
what's the benefit of using this guy?
Consider a function of this kind. Right?
At this location, if you're here, the
minimum is here. At this location, do
you want to be taking big steps or small
steps?
Do you want to be taking big small
steps? Right? Because you want to be
careful out here. Do you want to be big
taking big steps or small steps?
Big steps. So, when the derivative
magnitude is large, you want to take big
steps. When the derivative magnitude is
small, you know you're getting close. So
you want to take small steps. So this
this update rule actually captures this
principle very nicely which means you at
each point you take a step against the
derivative with some scaling factor that
we will discuss in later later lectures
and that should get you closer and
closer to the minimum. So is this whole
thing clear so far?
This entire thing clear so far?
Yes. No. Okay. And so that leaves us
leads us to our next poll.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
All right, let me end this.
Okay.
Uh, anybody want to answer? Is this
first statement true or false?
True or false? First one true. Second
one
true. Third one.
Third one is false. Right? There's
always the So at any location there are
many directions in which you can step
such that the function increases. The
direction of the gradient is the
direction in which it increases fastest.
The gradient is of course the transpose
of the derivative. And so here we are.
If you're in this function, if this is
your current estimate, you want to move
in this direction, the direction of the
gradient to if you want to maximize the
function, but you want to move in this
direction against the gradient exactly
opposite to the gradient if you want to
decrease the function. And so here is
the uh uh overall optimization rule. The
gradient ascent or the gradient descent
method to find the minimum or maximum of
a function does this. You start off with
an initial estimate. To find the maximum
at each point, you take a step exactly
in the direction of the gradient. to
find a minimum, which is what we want to
do in our problems because we're trying
to minimize a loss. You start off with
an initial estimate and then at the kth
step, you take a step against the
gradient of the function.
uh again computed at the current
position to
get the next estimate or the next uh
iterate iterate of the next estimate of
the solution. So did this make sense to
everybody what we've done so far?
Yes. Now
okay against is negative opposite the
gradient minus gradient. Okay.
So uh that's what and when do you stop
the gradient descent conver algorithm
converges when one of the following
criteria is satisfied either the
gradient becomes zero or the distance
between successive steps becomes very
small and this first one is a much
better choice than the second one. This
is not a great test and we will see why
this is the case uh in a later in this
lecture.
And so here is the overall gradient
descent algorithm. If you want to
minimize a function f with respect to x,
you initialize your estimate for for the
for the position of the minimum and then
you iteratively take this follow this
rule where you keep taking a step
opposite to the direction of the
gradient against the gradient and keep
doing this until the distance between
success of iterations becomes so small
that you're not gaining very much from
continuing this these iterations.
And how will it behave? So for an
appropriately
u for for good functions with nice
shapes like this bone right convex
functions this is the method of gradient
descent and it will always find the
minimum. For non-convex functions which
have crazy shapes like these it may find
a local minimum. It may find an
inflection point or a saddle point or
other such uh other such uh unnecessary
solutions also. Nonetheless, this is the
best thing we have given our current
problem. That is we have to find a
minimum. So that gives us our next goal.
Okay, this one's quick, so I'm only
going to give you 40 seconds, 20 more
seconds, guys.
5 seconds.
Okay, let me end this.
Uh, what is the answer?
three, right? Exactly opposite to the
direction of the gradient at x0.
Beautiful.
So, we've covered gradient descent. Now,
let's return to our problem from our
detour. Here is our problem. You're
given a set of training input output
pairs. The x input x and the desired
output the value of the function d. You
want to design this function f with
parameters w such that the average
divergence between the output of the
function and the desired output of the
function over all the training points
which is our loss is minimized. This
loss is function is a function of only
the network parameters. So we want to
minimize it with respect to these
network parameters w. This is a problem
of function minimization. So I can do it
using gradient descent. I can initialize
my network parameters and then
iteratively update the parameters using
the straightup gradient descent rule
where now it is the gradient of the loss
with respect to the uh network
parameters and you keep doing this till
the loss no longer changes
significantly.
But before we proceed,
so is this clear to everybody? Why we
using gradient descent?
Right? What is the appropriate value of
epsilon? You'll encounter that in your
homework. So we'll get to that.
Before we proceed, there are many things
we have to define. We haven't even
gotten close to setting the whole thing
up.
We want to minimize this loss with
respect to W which is the average
divergence between the actual and
desired outputs of the network. But to
do these many things have to be defined.
First, what are these input output
pairs? How do we define them? Second,
what is this function f and what what is
it exactly and what are its parameters?
Third, what is the form of this
divergence function? Without defining
these, the loss itself cannot be
defined.
So let's start with this question first.
What is f? Well, you know, we're going
to start with this because this is at
the core of the problem,
the network function itself. So what is
f for us? F is a neural network. It's a
multi-layer perceptron. We're going to
assume that the network is directed so
that uh when an input comes in each
layer of the network processes the input
just once and then passes it on to the
next layer till you get to the output
layer uh which produces the output of
the network. There are no loops
and furthermore we're going to assume
that the network is layered where a
layer is a set of neurons that are all
the same depth with respect to the input
as we saw. Now all networks are layered
by this definition. But the one extra
assumption over here is that all the
neurons in the output are at the same
depth with respect to the input just for
convenience. It's not necessary. We're
going to represent the input refer to
the inputs as the input layer. Although
we are calling it a layer, there are
actually no neurons out here. These are
just the inputs. It's just terminology.
We're going to call them input layers.
The set of output neurons, this is what
we call the output layer. And all the
layers in between, we're going to call
them hidden layers.
The individual neurons in this network
uh they're they're going to have the
standard structure. They operate on a
stand set of inputs to produce an
output. uh the neuron in the standard
setup the neuron first computes an
aphine function of its inputs which is a
weighted sum of the inputs plus a bias
to compute an aine term C and then
applies an activation function such as a
sigmoid root soft plus whatever on the Z
to generate the output more generally
however the neuron can be any
differentiable function of its inputs
but we are going to focus on this kind
of neuron
Now uh so this is the kind of neuron
we're going to assume we're going unless
otherwise specified
that we have a continuous activation
function applied to an aphine function
of the inputs of the neuron. So the
parameters of the neuron are the weights
and the bias.
Now there are a bunch of different
activation functions at this in this
regard. Uh here are some examples.
Historically the most popular was the
sigmoid. The sigmoid is 0 to the far
left, one to the far right, and goes
smoothly from the from 0 to one. We've
seen this formula before. And uh if you
look at the derivative of the sigma, and
you can work out the formula, but then
out to the far left, what is the
derivative going to be? What is the
derivative going to be out here to the
left? Anybody?
Zero. What is the derivative going to be
out here?
also zero. And so the derivative is
going to have this shape. It's going to
go from zero back to zero. And right in
the middle, it's going to have a value
of 0.25.
The tan h is just the sigmoid which is
sort of scaled and shifted. So this two
has the same shape of derivative then
shaped except out here the der in the
middle right here the derivative value
is going to be one. What will the
derivative of this relu function look
like? Anybody? What's the derivative to
the left out here? What's it? Zero,
right? What's the derivative to the
right?
One. And so the derivative is going to
look like this. It's zero to the left
and one to the right. For the soft plus,
the soft plus, the derivative is going
to look like a sigma.
So these are all the activation
functions and their derivatives.
Now,
uh,
so far I've assumed that a neuron takes
in a set of inputs and produces a single
output. But you can also have neurons
that produce a multiple outputs, a set
of outputs. We're going to call these
neurons vector activations. These vector
activations take a set of outputs,
inputs, and generate a set of outputs.
Now uh how does that uh actually make a
difference? We will see what this means
is that when you in your standard
setting the ones that we looked at
before
if you consider the parameters of the
network if you modify one parameter of
the network only one of these outputs
would have been modified. Now if you
modify a single parameter all of them
can be modified. So uh a very common
example for this to give you an idea is
the softmax activation. The softmax
activation first computes a bunch of
aphine values from the inputs. Then each
of these aphine values is exponentiated
so that out here you get the exponent
the exponentiation of z1. But then this
entire set is normalized by dividing by
the sum. So that the sum of all of these
outputs is one. Now what will happen?
Let's say I increase the weight of this
edge such that Z1 increases.
What will happen to Y1? Will it increase
or decrease?
If this weight, this W is increased
adjusted to increase Z1. Will Y1
increase or decrease?
What do you guys think?
What about Y2? Will it increase or
decrease?
Will Y2 increase or decrease
over here? It's got to decrease. Why?
Because if Y1 increases, because all of
them must sum to one. The rest of them
must decrease, right? And so here you
have an an activation function where
changing a parameter doesn't just change
one output. It changes the entire set of
outputs. This is what I call a vector
activation. Did that make sense to
everybody?
Does this make sense? Okay.
So I just got two yeses.
All right.
Now you you could in principle some
consider all of the neurons in a layer
together as being a single vector
activation. So I could just put a box
around all of these guys and say a bunch
of inputs are coming in a bunch of
outputs in outputs are coming out. And
this is perfectly true. So in fact even
disconnected neurons can be thought of
as a special case of vector activations.
And using this interpretation, every
layer in the network is a vector
activation where for some layers
changing a parameter will only change
one output whereas in other layers
changing a parameter could change all
outputs.
So we've defined this function f. It's a
neural network. Uh it's a multi-layer
perceptron and we've defined the
perceptron itself and we've talked about
the kinds of activations scalar and
vector activations.
this clear so far that we've covered f
and everything we've said about f has
been clear.
Okay, next thing right let's consider
these input output pairs.
What are these input output pairs?
Now in defining inputs and outputs there
are three things to consider. the input
to the network, the actual output of the
network and the desired output of the
network. So each training instance is
going to be a vector of this kind
corresponding to the vector if it's a if
the network is generating multiple
outputs there's going to be a desired
output which specifies what each of
these values must be ideally and there's
going to be an actual output which is
also a vector and the output of the
vector of network outputs must have the
same number of components as the vector
of desired outputs clearly because you
want this guy to be equal to this the
ideal right so are these three things
clear the three variables you must
consider the input the desired output
and the actual output of the network are
these clear to everybody
yes no okay
>> right
>> all right so
then how do you represent the input
Any input to the network is a vector of
numbers. What these net numbers are
depends on the type of input. For
images, they could be pixel values. For
a speech input, there could be a vector
of speech features. For text, this must
be a vector of real numbers that
represent the text. We'll discuss how we
get to this from text later in the
course. For other kinds of inputs too,
the input will eventually have to be a
vector of numbers derived from the
input.
Now, so this is easy. The input is just
a vector of numbers which could be pixel
values, speech features, something
derived from text, whatever else. I'm
going to assume that we know how to deal
with inputs. Eventually, we're going to
provide numbers through the network. The
more important thing is how do we
represent the output? The representation
of the output depends on the problem. If
you're trying to perform regression
where you're where you're trying to
compute real valued outputs numbers then
the output consists of real values
numbers. So if the desired output is a
scalar number
then like here like in scalar regression
then the network will have just one
output node with a real valid output and
typically in these settings the
activation function for this final layer
is just going to be an identity matrix
an identity transform. So the output is
simply going to be Z itself.
When you have uh when uh the network is
supposed to compute a vector of outputs
then the network will also have a a
number of output neurons in the in the
output layer where the number of neurons
is going to be exactly the same as the
dimensionality of the desired output.
And and once again in regression
problems the activation function that we
will use out here is just going to be a
linear activation or an identity
activation where the ZV value is not
transformed and just passed on directly.
Right? This making sense
over here I'm just saying this is a
vector. These are the components.
So each input is a vector. The desired
output is a vector and the actual output
is a vector. That answer see
okay and so
uh
all right
so representing the output for real
valued prediction. Was this clear to
everybody? Yes or no?
You're just going to use a network with
as many output neurons as the
dimensionality of the output you're
going to predict. And the activation
typically is a linear activation which
is just an identity transform.
But then if the desired output is binary
like in a binary classification task. So
here I can use a simple 1 0 to represent
the desired output. If I'm performing a
classification task like looking at an
image and saying is this a cat or is it
not a cat then the output is going to be
ideal outputs are going to be one for
yes it's a cat and zero for no it's not
a cat
and this is now this is the ideal output
the actual output of the network won't
be binary though the actual output of
the network will typically use a
continuous valued activation generally a
sigmoid because uh the sigmoid produces
an output between 0 and one and the
value of the sigmoid can be viewed as
the probability that the input belongs
to category one. So it's like taking a
uh picture of a cat and uh saying what
is taking a picture and saying what is
the probability that this is a cat
and more importantly the sigmoid is
differentiable and shiran a sigmoid is
just a special case of a softmax a
softmax is a multi-
multivaried version of a sigmoid
okay now
when for networks network that perform
multiclass classification that classify
inputs into more than one class. Then
for example a network that must dist for
for example a network that must
distinguish between say a cat, a dog, a
camel, a hat and a flower, five classes,
right?
Then we need a slightly more complex
representation of the network. If there
are n classes now the network will have
n outputs
and the desired output is represented.
Uh so here in our example because we
have five classes the network will have
five outputs.
And now in our arrangement we are going
to order all of our classes in some
canonical order. And anytime you have an
input that belongs to a particular
class, you're going to compose a vector
of this kind. So for example, if the
vector belongs to the class cat, then
the desired output is going to be zero
for all the other outputs and one in the
position of cat. If the desired output
is dog,
then the if if the category of the input
is dog, then the desired output is going
to be zero in all of the these positions
and a one in the position of dog. If the
desired output is camel in our canonical
order, camel comes third. So the third
output will be one, the rest will be
zero and so on. So is this
representation I can sense to you guys?
This is what's called a one hot
representation because only one of the
elements is one and the rest are zero.
The size of this vector is the same as
the number of classes. And the specific
element that's going to be one is the
element corresponding to the index of
the class in your standard order of
classes.
So
what was the question?
Is there a question?
Okay, maybe not. All right. So, all
right.
And so, here we are. Right.
For multiclass classifier with n
classes, the desired output will be an n
component one hot vector.
Uh, and it will have n binary components
only one of which will be one.
The network's actual output, that's the
desired output, right? The network's
actual output is also the also going to
have n components. But now the outputs
must ideally just be one hot also one
corresponding to the class of the input
and zero to the others. In reality, it
will be a probability vector, an n
component probability vector which
assigns probabilities to each of the
classes. And to obtain the output
probability vector in multiclass
classification problems, the output
layer is generally a soft max vector
activation whose formula we we've
already seen. I'm just repeating it over
here. So you get one value per class and
then you exponentiate them all and
normalize them. So the outputs sum to
one and so because they sum to one and
they're all positive these can be viewed
as a probabilities his probabilities and
so the output at each position
corresponds to the probability of that
class given the input. So if you had
cat, dog, camel and flower and you were
given an input, the network is going to
produce the probability that this this
is a cat that this is a dog, this is a
camel and this is a flower and this
probability must ideally match the one
hot representation that we had for a
training instance uh when we when we
train the network. So that make sense to
everybody?
That make sense to everybody? Okay.
>> I have a question.
>> Yeah.
>> Then how do we represent words? Uh that
like words with similar spelling but
different meaning like bank like bank of
>> not we have not yet we have not gone to
text at all. Text is way down. We're
going to talk about in a much later
class. We just say we're still setting
up the net. Okay.
>> Okay. Thank you.
But if you're if you were representing
words, if you're trying to classify, you
know, an image, if you're doing an opt
optical character recognizer and trying
to recognize words, then your words
would be arranged in a canonical lexical
order. And for each input, you would
have a one hot representation with a
one. For each training input, you would
have a one hot representation with a one
in the position of the word in the
dictionary order and zero elsewhere.
That make sense?
>> Yes.
>> You're still going to converting
everything to one hot representations.
And so here is the typical
uh problem statement. If you're if
you're performing binary classification,
say you're going to try to recognize
images and say this is a digit two.
You'd be given digits and their labels.
the desired output of the digit which
will be one a one or zero label telling
you whether it's whether it's a two or
not and uh so the image here is an
arrangement of pixel values
the this is what the desired output is
binary one's a one or zero and the
network output will output will be a
scaler from a sigmoid activation we'd
have to learn the network parameters to
make the output match this binary label
exactly
and so this is What you'd have for
binary classification, you'd have a
bunch of digits corresponding to each
digit. You'd have a label one or zero
telling you whether it's a two or not.
The network would have an architecture
like this. And you're going to train the
network so that so that the output
matches one as closely as possible when
the input is two and zero as closely as
possible when the input is not two.
For the multiclass classification
problem, we'd be given images and when
now we'll actually be given the classes.
So if you were trying to recognize
digits, uh the label for each input is
going to be the uh the digit itself. And
the network itself is going to be and
and for training you're going to be
converting these labels to one hot
vectors.
The network's output layer if you're
recognizing digits is would be a 10
component soft max. And we'd learn
network parameters to minimize the error
between the softmax output and these
given labels. Basically to make sure
that the probability of the correct
class uh is as close to one as possible
and the probability of the incorrect
classes is as close to zero as possible
when these inputs are provided. That
make sense to everybody?
So,
uh, we've defined most things. I'm
seeing a few yeses. I'll go with that.
Right.
So, how is the exponential used with the
one hot vector? The one hot vector is
your desired output.
So, if I got this guy, right, or if I
got this guy, then that's the number
two. So, I want a zero out here. This
represents one. One. This is my desired
output.
The network is going to use a soft max
to produce four outputs over here. And
these are the probabilities of the four
digits. Ideally, you want this guy to be
as close to this to be one and these to
be zero. That answer your question even
the exponentiation happens inside the
softness. It has nothing to do with the
one hot. The one hot is the target
output. That answer your question.
Still I have some difficulty understand
um how this exponential
came into the picture but is
>> the exponential the exponential is just
a part of the soft max that's how we
compute the softmax uh so if I go back
here
a few in a soft max the computation in a
softmax is two step first you compute an
aine value z for each of these inputs
for each of these classes then these
aphine value Z is exponentiated. The
thing with exponentiation is that the
output is always one. So somewhere in
here you're going to be computing X of Z
from each of these Z's. Then you
normalize by the sum. And so this guy is
going to be this normalized exponents
which sum to one. So the exponentiation
happens inside the softness. Uh did that
answer your question? Amen.
If that did not then let's take it off
to Piaza because we have to move on
right because we have one more thing to
discuss. We've defined a function. We
have defined the inputs and outputs
but we still have to define this
divergence function that quantifies the
error between the actual and desired
outputs.
And very important for this loss to be
differentiable. It's not enough for the
network to be differentiable with
respect to w. This divergence function
must be differentiable with respect to
f. Otherwise you cannot figure out how
perturbing a small the w a little bit
will will modify the overall loss.
Now when the desired output of the So
did this make sense that the divergence
must be differential everybody?
Yes or no?
Yes. No. Okay. All right. So let me
continue.
Now when the desired output of the
network is real valued a real valued
scalar or vector like in a regression
problem then there's a natural choice
for the divergence function which is the
L2 divergence which is defined like so
half of the squared uh uklidian distance
between the network output and the
desired output which is again written as
half of sum over all components of the
square of the error between the output
corresponding component of the output
and the same comp same component of the
desired output. So this half is only for
convenience. When you differentiate it,
the two comes out here and cancel out
cancels out the two and the half. And so
when you take the derivative of this guy
with respect to y, that simply becomes y
-
okay. Now note that y - d²
is the same as dus y^ 2. Right? So when
I differentiated it, why did I get y - d
and not d minus y?
You can work through the math, but
there's a very simple logic that you can
think. So let's say d is my desired
output. If my current output is y and y
is greater than d, will increasing y
increase the error or decrease the error
in the setting?
Will increasing Y decre increase Y or
increase or decrease the error in the
setting? It will increase it. So what is
the derivative of the loss with respect
to Y? Is it going to be positive or
negative?
Positive. On the other hand, if Y is
less than D, will increasing Y increase
or decrease the error
over here? If y is less than d, will
increasing y increase or decrease the f?
It's going to decrease the f. What's the
derivative going to be? Negative or
positive
over here.
Will the derivative of the loss with
respect to y be negative or positive? In
this case guys, increasing y decreases
the loss.
Did I lose you guys? It's going to be
negative, right? It's always going to be
negative. So you can see this when y is
greater than d this is positive because
you end up in this setting
increasing y increases the error. When y
is less than d this is negative because
you end up in this setting increasing y
decreases the error. So you can see
that's why it has to be y - d and not d
minus y. That make sense to everybody?
The sign over here?
Yes. Huh?
Okay. Uh let me continue
for binary classification when I have uh
a binary classified file. So I want the
output to be either one or zero.
So let's say the network I can always
use a I'm going to use a a sigmoid. I
can always use the L2 loss as before.
But there's another loss which is
better. And for that let's uh uh let's
design the loss.
Let's say the desired output is one.
But the network says the probability
that belong this belongs to class one is
zero. Is this just somewhat wrong or
infinitely wrong?
The class is one but the network says
that it's the probability that it's one
is zero. It's infinitely wrong. Right?
So when d is 1 and y is zero, it must be
infinitely wrong. Correct?
What kind of function gives me this?
It's d * log of y,
right? But then I need a minus because
log of 0 is minus infinity. This works
for d equals 1. It doesn't work for d
equals 0 because this becomes zero. for
D equals Z.
If the network is 100%
positive that it belongs to class one,
then what's it like? Is it just wrong or
infinitely wrong?
If D is zero, the network it's it's
infinitely wrong. Right? So here I'm
going to say log of 1 - Y
* 1 - D. And so you can see the sum. So
the overall loss has this property. It's
this guy. D log minus D log Y minus 1 -
D log 1 - Y. And you can see why this
makes sense, right? So where do we get
the probability? That's the that's the
output of the network, right? The
sigmoid generates the probability. And
so uh this is the callback library
dimensions. Here's what the callback
library dimensions looks like. You can
see that uh uh the output the
probability is between 0 and one
and let's say that desired probability
is zero and the uh actual
and uh the probability output by the
network varies from 0 to one. The
divergence is zero when the two are the
same. But if the network outputs a
probability of one is very certain that
it belongs to class one, the divergence
is infinity. Similarly, if the desired
output is class one, but the network is
100% certain that it belongs to class
zero. Once again, the uh class the uh
error is infinity. So you know you're
predicting the probability of class of
the label. You're not directly
predicting the label, right? And so you
see this, right? Do you see why this
makes sense? Guys, I'm going to go a few
minutes over. Please bear with me. One
of the outcomes of this is that when you
take the derivative of this guy, when d
is 1, the derivative is minus 1 / y.
When d is zero, this goes away. The
derivative is 1 / 1 - y. Just the
straight up derivative of this guy. And
so observe something very interesting
over here.
And if the desired output is 1 and y is
also 1, the derivative is minus of 1 / 1
which is -1. The derivative is not zero
when the network is correct. So also
over here if the desired output is zero
and the network's output output is also
zero the derivative is 1 / 1 which is
one. So you can see that the slope over
here when the desired output is zero the
derivative of the loss is one is one.
When the desired output is one you can
see that the derivative of the loss is
minus one. Which is why simply looking
at the magnitude of the derivative is
not a great thing to do when you are
trying to uh perform gradient descent.
You want to see the actual losses
decreasing. This make sense to all of
you guys? ratio over here.
Right? So to all the rest of you that
make sense? Okay.
And then for multiclass classification
we have a very similar thing. Uh we're
going to define the callback labler
divergence except the callback label
divergence is not defined as summation d
log d / y which is summation d log d
minus d log y. But then the desired
output is always either one or zero.
Right? So when if the desired output is
zero, this term becomes zero. If the
desired output of is one, log of one is
zero. So this also becomes zero. So this
first term simply disappears.
The second term, the desired output is
going to be zero for all the wrong
classes. It's going to be one only for
the correct things. So this entire term
simply collapses to minus of log of the
probability assigned to the correct
class. Did this make sense to you guys
that the KL divergence simply becomes
the pro minus of and you can see right
when you're minimizing the loss you're
minimizing minus log Y which is to say
you're maximizing log Y. And so
minimizing the loss means that you're
maximizing the probability of the
correct case which makes sense. And once
again if you take the derivative of this
loss with respect to the outputs of the
network since only the probability of
the correct class figures over here the
derivative is going to be zero for all
the other classes and minus1 over the
probability of the correct class
for the correct class. And always you
can see that this term is always
negative because y is always positive
which means that it's always telling you
that increasing the probability of the
correct class decreases the loss.
So so far so good
and once again note that when y is
equals to t so if y is one for the
correct loss the derivative although the
divergence becomes zero the derivative
is non zero.
And one last thing uh in all of your
homeworks you're going to be think
speaking of the cross entropy loss
rather than the callback lard
divergence.
If you work it out in the callback
lambda divergence we saw this term
always become zero. So you're only left
with this guy. This term is what we call
the cross entropy loss. So when your
target is represented as a one hot
vector the cross entropy loss and the
callback ler divergence are exactly the
same thing
and moreover we saw it collapses to
minus log of the probability of the
correct loss
in my lectures I'm going to keep
speaking of the kback labler divergence
but just remember that the cross entropy
loss and the kback l divergence are the
same thing when you use the one hot
vector for representing the term it up
that make sense to everybody?
Yes. No,
it's okay.
And final thing, right? The very last
point, when I use the KL divergence, I
can take the derivative of the KL
divergence with respect to the output of
the soft max and then I can take the
derivative of that with respect to the
input to the soft max, which is the
aphine term. If you work out the
arithmetic, it turns out that this
derivative is simply the error between
the desired out between the actual
output of the network and the desired
output of the network. So something very
interesting pops up over here namely
that uh regardless of whether you're
performing regression or classification
in regression problems the output
activation is identity and we saw that
the loss of the lo the derivative of the
loss with respect to the aine term is
simply the error between the output and
the derivative for classification also
if you're using the kale divergence or
the cross entropy loss. Then the
derivative of the loss with respect to
the aine term that goes into the softmax
is also just the error of the network
which is the error between the actual
output of the softmax and the desired
output of the softmax. This making sense
to everybody?
Yes. Now
y minus d. So the derivative with
respect to the aphine term is always the
error which is why we always called it
error back propagation. And so in the
problem setup we have defined all of our
terms and so we're good to go. I have a
poll uh I'll skip it but the story so
far neural networks are universal
approximators. They are trained to
approximate functions by adjusting their
parameters to minimize the average
divergence between their actual output
and the desired output. To train them,
many terms must be defined. The network
itself, the manner in which inputs are
represented, the manner in which outputs
are represented and the divergence
function that computes the error between
the actual and desired outputs.
Once we define all of these, we are set
to train the network. And for that,
we're going to have to figure out how to
compute derivatives for which we use
back propagation, which we will discuss
in the next class. Thank you for your
patience. I apologize for going a few
minutes over.